Tom L Jenkins

PhD

Curriculum Vitae



tomjenkins.netlify.app

Tom-Jenkins

Profile

Scientist specialising in bioinformatics, data analysis and R programming. I have a broad range of experience and knowledge in evolutionary biology, geospatial analysis and data science. Previous projects include population genomics and whole genome sequencing of marine species, genome assembly and trait-association modelling, and predicting habitat suitability using machine learning.

Employment

Apr 2022-Present Bioinformatician & Software Developer Animal and Plant Health Agency

Feb 2021–Mar 2022 Senior Data Analyst / Advisor Natural England
Dec 2018–Jan 2021 Postdoctoral Research Associate University of Exeter

Qualifications

2018	PhD	Biological Sciences	University of Exeter
2014	MRes	Biodiversity Informatics and Genomics	Imperial Colleage London
2010	BSc	Marine Biology	Swansea University

Computer Skills

Proficient R Programming, Linux, Geocomputation, MS Office
Competent GitHub, AWS, R Markdown, R Shiny, Leaflet.js, ECharts.js
Developing Nextflow, JavaScript

Selected Communication and Awards

2022	Interview	Live interview on BBC Radio Wales Drive to discuss published research on coral	
		habitat suitability modelling	
2021	Interview	Pre-recorded interview on BBC Radio Cornwall to discuss published research on	
		red algae population genomics	
2019	Award	British Ecological Society Research Grant (£5,000)	
2018	Talk	Invited talk at Aquaculture Research Collaborative Hub UK Annual Conference	
2018	Award	Heredity Fieldwork Grant (£1,284)	

Selected Publications

- ➤ Jenkins TL, Stevens JR (2022). Predicting habitat suitability and range shifts under projected climate change for two octocorals in the north-east Atlantic. PeerJ 10, e13509.
- ➤ Jenkins TL, Guillemin M-L, Simon-Nutbrown C, Burdett HL, Stevens JR, Peña V (2021). Whole genome genotyping reveals discrete genetic diversity in north-east Atlantic maerl beds. Evolutionary Applications 14, 1558–1571.
- ➤ Houston RD, Bean TP, Macqueen DJ, Gundappa MK, Jin YH, **Jenkins TL**, *et al.* (2020). Harnessing genomics to fast-track genetic improvement in aquaculture. Nature Reviews Genetics 21, 389–409.